Here's a question. How do submarines
know where they are? I mean, near the
surface, they can just stick out an
antenna above the water to use GPS. But
if the antenna is even a couple of
centimeters below the surface, the GPS
will stop working because it uses radio
waves that are easily absorbed by
seawater. So, as an alternative, a
submarine can actually use its sonar to
map out the seafloor, and then it can
compare those maps to maps that [music]
were made in the past. But if you're
trying to stay hidden in your submarine,
blasting loud sonar waves probably isn't
a good idea. So most submarines rely on
something quieter. To work out which way
the sub is pointing, they use something
called a fiber optic gyroscope. What it
does is it sends two beams of light
around a fiber optic coil in opposite
directions. [music]
And then when the submarine turns, the
rotation is going to change the distance
each beam has to travel, meaning they're
going to return slightly out of phase.
And that [music] tiny mismatch can be
used to work out how much the submarine
is rotating. And to work out how far a
submarine has moved, [music] they use an
accelerometer. So a common design uses a
tiny weight that is attached to this
thin beam of crystalline quartz, which
is kept constantly vibrating at its
[music] natural frequency. It's kind of
like a guitar string. Then when the
submarine accelerates, the weight's
inertia pulls or pushes on the beam,
which puts it under tension or
compression. And just like tightening a
guitar string raises [music] its pitch,
that changes the frequency at which the
quartz vibrates. And by measuring that
tiny shift in frequency, [music] the
computer can work out the acceleration
and from that the position and how far
the submarine has moved.